Cancer? Heart attacks? Diabetes?
السرطان؟ الأزمات القلبية؟ مرض السكر؟
The answer is actually none of these;
الإجابة حقيقةً ليس أولئك؛
it's Alzheimer's disease.
بل مرض الزهايمر.
Every 67 seconds,
كل 67 ثانية،
someone in the United States is diagnosed with Alzheimer's.
شخص في أمريكا تشخص إصابته بالزهايمر.
As the number of Alzheimer's patients triples by the year 2050,
ما يعني أن بحلول 2050 يصل عدد مرضى الزهايمر ثلاثة أضعاف،
caring for them, as well as the rest of the aging population,
العناية بهم، بالإضافة إلى بقية السكان المسنين،
will become an overwhelming societal challenge.
سوف تصبح تحدي مجتمعي ساحق.
My family has experienced firsthand
خاضت عائلتي تجربة كفاح العناية
the struggles of caring for an Alzheimer's patient.
بمريض زهايمر.
Growing up in a family with three generations,
نشأتي في عائلة ذات ثلاث أجيال،
I've always been very close to my grandfather.
جعلني قريب جدًا من جدي.
When I was four years old,
حين كنت في الرابعة،
my grandfather and I were walking in a park in Japan
بينما كنت وجدي نتجول في منتزه باليابان
when he suddenly got lost.
لم أجده فجأة.
It was one of the scariest moments I've ever experienced in my life,
كانت واحدة من اللحظات المرعبة التي عانيت منها في حياتي،
and it was also the first instance that informed us
وكانت أيضًا أول مثل أعلمنا
that my grandfather had Alzheimer's disease.
أن جدي مصاب بالزهايمر.
Over the past 12 years, his condition got worse and worse,
خلال ال 12 سنة الماضية، تحولت حالته من أسوء لأسوء،
and his wandering in particular caused my family a lot of stress.
وخاصة هيامه على وجهه تسبب في كثير من الإجهاد لأسرتي.
My aunt, his primary caregiver,
عمتي، راعيته الأساسية،
really struggled to stay awake at night to keep an eye on him,
كافحت حقًا لتبقى مستيقظة ليلًا لتراقبه،
and even then often failed to catch him leaving the bed.
ورغم ذلك تفشل غالبًا في ضبطه يغادر الفراش.
I became really concerned about my aunt's well-being
أصبحت حقًا مهتم براحة عمتي
as well as my grandfather's safety.
بالإضافة إلى أمان جدي.
I searched extensively for a solution that could help my family's problems,
بحثت بطريقة موسعة عن حل يمكن أن يساعد في حل مشكلات عائلتي،
but couldn't find one.
لكن لم استطيع إيجاد واحد.
Then, one night about two years ago,
ثم، ذات ليلة منذ عامين،
I was looking after my grandfather and I saw him stepping out of the bed.
كنت أراقب جدي ورأيته يخرج من فراشه.
The moment his foot landed on the floor,
في اللحظة التي وضع فيها قدمه على الأرض،
I thought, why don't I put a pressure sensor on the heel of his foot?
فكرت، لماذا لا أضع مستشعر ضغط على كعب رجله؟
Once he stepped onto the floor and out of the bed,
بمجرد أن يخرج من الفراش ويخطو على الأرض،
the pressure sensor would detect an increase in pressure caused by body weight
مستشعر الضغط سيستشعر زيادة الضغط الناتج عن وزن الجسم
and then wirelessly send an audible alert to the caregiver's smartphone.
ثم يرسل لاسلكيًا لهاتف مقدم الرعاية إنذار صوتي.
That way, my aunt could sleep much better at night
بهذه الطريقة، يمكن أن تنام عمتي أفضل بالليل
without having to worry about my grandfather's wandering.
دون قلق من أن يهيم جدي على وجه.
So now I'd like to perform a demonstration of this sock.
إذًا الآن أود أن أقدم شرح لهذا الجورب.
Could I please have my sock model on the stage?
هل يمكن أن أحضر نموذج جوربي على المسرح؟
Great.
عظيم.
So once the patient steps onto the floor --
إذًا بمجرد أن يخطو المريض على الأرض ــ
(Ringing) --
(رنين)ــ
an alert is sent to the caregiver's smartphone.
يُرسل إنذار لهاتف مقدم الرعاية.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرًا. (تصفيق)
Thank you, sock model.
شكرًا، نموذج الجورب.
So this is a drawing of my preliminary design.
حسنًا، هذا رسم لتصميمي المبدئ.
My desire to create a sensor-based technology
رغبتي لإنشاء مستشعر تكنولوجي
perhaps stemmed from my lifelong love for sensors and technology.
ربما تنبع من حبي طول عمري للمستشعرات والتكنولوجيا.
When I was six years old,
حين كنت في السادسة،
an elderly family friend fell down in the bathroom
سقط في الحمام صديق مسن للعائلة
and suffered severe injuries.
وأصيب بجروح حادة.
I became concerned about my own grandparents
أصبحت مهتم بأجدادي
and decided to invent a smart bathroom system.
وقررت اخترع نظام حمام ذكي.
Motion sensors would be installed inside the tiles of bathroom floors
يجب إدراج مستشعر حركة داخل بلاطات أرضية الحمام
to detect the falls of elderly patients whenever they fell down in the bathroom.
لتشعر بسقوط المرضى المسنين وقتما يسقطون في الحمام.
Since I was only six years old at the time
منذ أن كنت في السادسة فقط في وقت
and I hadn't graduated from kindergarten yet,
لم أكن قد تخرجت من بعد من روضة الأطفال،
I didn't have the necessary resources and tools to translate my idea into reality,
لم أكن أملك المصادر الضرورية والأدوات لترجمة أفكاري لحقيقة،
but nonetheless, my research experience
لكن مع ذلك، خبرة بحثي
really implanted in me a firm desire to use sensors to help the elderly people.
غرست بي حقًا رغبة راسخة لاستخدم المستشعرات لمساعدة المسنين.
I really believe that sensors can improve the quality of life of the elderly.
أؤمن حقًا أن المستشعرات تستطيع تحسين طبيعة الحياة للمسنين.
When I laid out my plan, I realized that I faced three main challenges:
حين وضعت خطتي، أدركت أني أواجه ثلاثة تحديات:
first, creating a sensor;
أولًا، إنشاء مستشعر؛
second, designing a circuit;
ثانيًا، تصميم دائرة كهربية؛
and third, coding a smartphone app.
ثالثًا، صياغة رموز تشفيرية لتطبيق هاتف ذكي.
This made me realize that my project was actually much harder to realize
ذلك جعلني أدرك أن مشروعي كان حقيقةً صعب التحقيق
than I initially had thought it to be.
مما كنت اعتقد في بادئ الأمر.
First, I had to create a wearable sensor that was thin and flexible enough
أولًا، كان علي أن أنشيء مستشعر يمكن ارتداءه، مستشعر رفيع ومرن كفاية
to be worn comfortably on the bottom of the patient's foot.
ليكون مريح للمريض عندما يرتديه في أسفل قدمه.
After extensive research and testing of different materials like rubber,
بعد بحث موسع واختبار مواد مختلفة مثل المطاط،
which I realized was too thick to be worn snugly on the bottom of the foot,
الذي أدركت أنه سميك جدًا ليكون مريحًا أثناء ارتداءه في باطن القدم،
I decided to print a film sensor
قررت أن أطبع مستشعر شريطي
with electrically conductive pressure-sensitive ink particles.
عليه جزيئات توصيل إلكترونية حساسة للضغط.
Once pressure is applied, the connectivity between the particles increases.
بمجرد الضغط، يزداد التوصيل بين الجزيئات.
Therefore, I could design a circuit that would measure pressure
علاوة على ذلك، يجب أن أصمم دائرة لتقيس الضغط
by measuring electrical resistance.
عن طريق قياس المقاومة الكهربية.
Next, I had to design a wearable wireless circuit,
ثانيًا، كان علي تصميم دائرة لاسلكية يمكن ارتداءها،
but wireless signal transmission consumes lots of power
لكن انبعاث إشارة لاسلكية يستهلك كثير من الطاقة
and requires heavy, bulky batteries.
ويتطلب بطاريات ضخمة وثقيلة.
Thankfully, I was able to find out about the Bluetooth low energy technology,
لله الحمد، كان لدي المقدرة لاكتشف البلوتوث، التكنولوجيا قليلة الطاقة،
which consumes very little power and can be driven by a coin-sized battery.
التي تستهلك طاقة قليلة جدًا ويمكن تشغيلها ببطارية في حجم العملة.
This prevented the system from dying in the middle of the night.
هذا يحمي النظام من التوقف في منتصف الليل.
Lastly, I had to code a smartphone app that would essentially transform
أخيرًا، كان علي تشفير تطبيق هاتف ذكي يمكنه في الأساس تحويل
the care-giver's smartphone into a remote monitor.
الهاتف الذكي لمقدم الرعاية لمراقب عن بعد.
For this, I had to expand upon my knowledge of coding with Java and XCode
لهذا، كان علي توسيع معرفتي بالتشفير عن طريق الجافا والإكس كود
and I also had to learn about how to code for Bluetooth low energy devices
وكان علي أيضًا أن أتعلم كيف أشفر أجهزة البلوتوث منخفضة الطاقة
by watching YouTube tutorials and reading various textbooks.
بمشاهدة دروس اليوتيوب وقراءة كتب عديدة.
Integrating these components, I was able to successfully create two prototypes,
بدمج تلك المكونات، كان بمقدرتي أن أنشيء بنجاح نموذجين بدء،
one in which the sensor is embedded inside a sock,
أحدهم المستشعر الذي يدمج داخل الجورب،
and another that's a re-attachable sensor assembly
والآخر المستشعر الملحق
that can be adhered anywhere that makes contact
الذي يمكنه أن يلحق بأي مكان ينشئ اتصال
with the bottom of the patient's foot.
بباطن قدم المريض.
I've tested the device on my grandfather for about a year now,
قد اختبرت الجهاز على جدي منذ حوالي عام الآن،
and it's had a 100 percent success rate
وقد حاز على معدل نجاح 100%
in detecting the over 900 known cases of his wandering.
في كشف أكثر من 900 حالة معروفة من تجواله.
Last summer, I was able to beta test my device
الصيف الماضي، كنت قادر على إجراء اختبار نهائي لجهازي
and I'm currently incorporating the feedback
وحاليًا أدمج الملاحظات
to further improve the device into a marketable product.
لمزيد من التطوير ليمكن تسويقه.
Testing the device on a number of patients
اختبار الجهاز على عدد من المرضى
made me realize that I needed to invent solutions
جعلني أدرك أني بحاجة لأخترع حل
for people who didn't want to wear socks to sleep at night.
للناس الذين لا يريدون ارتداء جوارب أثناء النوم ليلًا.
So sensor data, collected on a vast number of patients,
إذًا بيانات المستشعر، التي جمعت من عدد مرضى كبير،
can be useful for improving patient care
يمكن أن تكون مفيدة في تطوير رعاية المريض
and also leading to a cure for the disease, possibly.
وأيضًا من المحتمل أن تؤدي لشفاء المرض.
For example, I'm currently examining
على سبيل المثال، حاليًا اختبر
correlations between the frequency of a patient's nightly wandering
العلاقة المتبادلة بين تكرر تجوال المريض ليلًا
and his or her daily activities and diet.
ونشاطه اليومي ونظامه الغذائي.
One thing I'll never forget is when my device first caught
الشيء الذي لن أنساه أبدًا هو حين كشف جهازي لأول مرة
my grandfather's wandering out of bed at night.
تجول جدي ليلًا.
At that moment, I was really struck by the power of technology
في تلك اللحظة، أدهشتني حقًا قدرة التكنولوجيا
to change lives for the better.
على تغير الحياة للأفضل.
People living happily and healthfully --
يعيش الناس سعداء وأصحاء ــ
that's the world that I imagine.
هذا هو العالم الذي أتخيله.
Thank you very much.
أشكركم جدًا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)